Hi, welcome back to the Wheel of Life
online retreat. This fourth session
is going to be a meditation. We're going to
use the seven preliminary practices for
meditation that we learned in the second
segment, and we're going try to have what
we call a nam chi (NAM 'CHI). nam chi means: can we
recreate the experience of dying in
meditation? Can we try to recreate
what it's going to feel like as we die? And
then can we create new pathways in our
mind that are going to kick in ... they're
going to affect how we die. And we're going to
do a meditation that my teacher asked me
to do every night. So, of course we do our
coffee meditation at night, just as we're
falling to sleep, but there is a
tradition to practice dying as we fall
asleep--because falling asleep is also a
kind of a loss of our rough
consciousness.
So, let's start our practice dying
meditation. And the picture I chose for
this meditation is a guy, he's trying
to cut the wire of a bomb. And that's
what we want to do also. We don't want
one of our old bad seeds--doesn't
matter which priority--we don't want any
of them to blow up in the moment that we
die. We talked about four kinds of bad
seeds
fighting with each other--which one's
going to open first? But we're going to use
the daily practice of dying as we go to
sleep to get used to calling up a good
seed as our consciousness drifts
off.
Okay, so here we go. Let's meditate.
Sit up straight. The lower
abdomen is slightly pulled in. You do
that by exhaling extra when you come
to the end of your breath. Little bit of
a smile. Even though your eyelids are
closed, if you gaze a little bit up ...
slightly, slightly up--not much. As if you
were looking at the sun setting or
something. That will help you stay more
bright during your meditation. Okay, here
we go. Let's take ten deep breaths. Deep
exhales. Extra air going out at the end
of the exhale.
Don't worry about the inhale, he will
take care of himself.
Here we go. Start number one with the
exhale.
First of the seven preliminary steps:
please invite one of your teachers to
come and sit with you.
Now think about something you really
loved about this teacher. Some quality
about them that you really love. This is
also part of the first step, which is
honoring this teacher.
That also covers the second step: what
makes our teacher most happy--the biggest
gift we can make our teacher is to do
good deeds. And just thinking about the
very high good qualities of our teacher
is one of the best good karmas we can
make. And when we make good karmas for
ourselves, that's the greatest gift we
can give to our teacher. So, appreciate
something about your teacher as a gift.
Now think of some negative seed you
planted in the last 24 hours and regret
it, and make some commitment to try not
to do it in the next 24 hours.
Now, equal time, equal attention, great
appreciation for something nice you've
done in the last 24 hours.
Then ask your teacher to continue
teaching you.
Then ask your teacher to stay in your
life. Again, I like to spend about ten
breaths on each of these steps. Sometimes twenty breaths if I want to enjoy
them longer.
Now we'll start the actual meditation.
Again, that seventh preliminary step
actually comes after the meditation. So,
after the meditation we'll do the
dedication. Let's go through those four
priorities of our seeds that's going to
be triggered at the last moment of our
gross consciousness during death. Our
awareness of this world, this life, it
will end, and then our awareness will go
back to some very primitive basic
awareness that we've always had in our
many lifetimes.
We talked about the bad seeds before, but
now in this meditation, and for the rest
of your life, when you go to sleep you
can do this meditation. Number one:
first-in/first-out.
What was a very early good
karma I can remember doing? Maybe I was a
little kid in the school, maybe I helped
another child in the school to do their
homework or something.
What's an early good karma in my life
that I can still remember? Normally, that
one will open first as I die, so
please go ahead and think of something
sweet you did. Even a small thing as a
small child.
Now normally that seed, because it was
first in, would be first out. So, you could
expect it perhaps to open early as
you die, but maybe there's other seeds
that you planted later in your life--
maybe in your twenties. Good actions that
you repeated over and over. Maybe you
were a volunteer for some kind of charity,
and maybe one day a week for a year,
you donated your time. So that good
seed is going to push back the other one,
and it's going to be the seed that opens
as you die.
Imagine dying and this seed opening.
Again, dying is not losing all
consciousness; it's the the end of the
gross [@opposite of subtle] awareness of this life, and then
suddenly you're just back to a very
basic, almost animal, awareness.
Try to imagine where that habitual good seed--maybe work for a charity--
what kind of lifetime would it project
for you? What kind of lifetime might
it create? Maybe a very happy life where
people are always helping you.
Now, the next one we can only imagine.
Suppose we are actually in the hospital,
we are dying--again, which just means that
the awareness is going to drop from a
detailed awareness of this life to sort
of a very basic primitive awareness--and
suppose that a relative of ours just
runs their hand down our arm with a lot
of love. Just lightly they brush our arm
with love. They run their hand down their
arm. And that touch on my arm reminds me
of years ago a friend of mine--maybe
someone they loved--died and then I went
to their house and I was running my hand
down their arm to comfort them.
And so at the most crucial moment of my
life, as my rough mind stops,
I remember something kind and
considerate I did many years ago. And
that seed inserts itself at that moment
between the end of this life and going
back to my very basic state of mind.
That memory of serving someone at the
crucial moment of my death, it's going to
create a very beautiful future life.
Now, suppose instead that in those last
moments of this life
I remembered the very, very best good
karma I ever did in my whole life.
Maybe I saved someone's life.
Maybe I gave a lot of my money to
someone who needed it. Try to remember ...
and we're going to spend more time here. Try
to remember the very, very best karma you
ever planted in your whole life.
Now imagine that your new life is
beginning from this very, very powerful
good seed. If that whole
life is defined by that one incredible
good seed, what would that life be like?
We've finished the meditation. It's time
to do the seventh and final meditation
preliminary, which is actually not a
preliminary because it comes after the
meditation. But, just thinking about all
those good seeds fighting for first
position in our death, we made a lot of
good seeds just by thinking about our
good seeds. So, let's give those seeds
away as golden light. Three long, happy
exhales... the golden light... sharing those
seeds with the whole world.
And then slowly open your eyes. Take a good
stretch. And we'll see you for session
five of our lam rim Wheel of Life. Thank you.